<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="stylesheet.xsl"?>

<document type="article">
  <title>Coffee for one</title>
  <description>How I make coffee with a hand grinder and an Aeropress.</description>
  <slug>/posts/coffee-for-one</slug>
  <content>
    <article>
      <title>Coffee for one</title>
      <date datetime="2015-07">July 2015</date>
      <content>
        <p>For a long time, I made coffee with a cafetière. I make coffee one cup at a time and, whilst a cafetière is great for multiple cups, it wasn't great for me. They're fiddly to clean, can leave sediment in the coffee, and break when dropped.</p>

        <p>This year I've completely changed my coffee setup. It's optimised for brewing a single cup at a time at the weekend, so takes a little more time, but makes a really nice cup of coffee. If I did this during the week I'd buy pre-ground coffee since I'd use it faster and so be less concerned about its freshness.</p>

        <h2>The coffee-making process</h2>

        <p>I start with some nice, local, Small Batch beans.</p>

        <img src="/images/coffee.jpg" alt="Small Batch coffee beans" />

        <p>The beans are ground in my Hario Mini Mill.</p>

        <img src="/images/grinder.jpg" alt="Hario Mini Mill" />

        <p>I weigh the beans out - 17-20g depending on my caffeine requirement.</p>

        <img src="/images/grinder-beans.jpg" alt="Coffee beans on scales" />

        <p>Then grind away until they're all done. I'm playing with grind sizes, and at the moment it's #8 on this grinder.</p>

        <img src="/images/grinder-full.jpg" alt="Ground coffee in grinder" />

        <p>Maybe a little coarse, but it makes a nice cup.</p>

        <img src="/images/grounds.jpg" alt="Close-up of ground coffee" />

        <p>Now add water and brew.</p>

        <img src="/images/aeropress-brew.jpg" alt="Coffee brewing in Aeropress" />

        <p>Press into the mug. Slowly does it&#2026;</p>

        <img src="/images/aeropress-done.jpg" alt="Aeropress on coffee mug" />

        <p>And now, it's time to drink.</p>

        <img src="/images/mug.jpg" alt="Mug of coffee" />

        <p>I really like this setup. Once the coffee's done I just eject the grounds from the Aeropress, then give it and the grinder a rinse. The only perishable items are the Aeropress filters, and one pack lasts forever. If you're making coffee for one, I'd definitely recommend this method.</p>
      </content>
    </article>
  </content>
</document>
